[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha described in the Mahamangala Sutta as the first blessing, the avoidance of fools, association with the wise and the honoring of that which is worthy of honor.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do I find out what is worthy of honor and how do I truly venerate it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, I mean, you have to learn about it to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is useful, what is worth developing, what is worth investing effort in, in terms of the training, in terms of the practice, in terms of the dispassion, and then honor it by doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not honor it by setting up a shrine that you will bow to once every two weeks and in return it will do the work for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, have an attitude of respect towards that which is worth developing, which is virtue, restraining of your senses, taming down the mind, and basically aiming for dispassion in all areas of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, venerating it, respecting it in that sense, helps.
[SPEAKER_01]: Helps maintain the context, helps you have the energy and inspiration to kind of, you know, go further, because you're not being casual about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it does not mean, as I said, just sort of make a shrine out of it and worship it like a deity or some sort of holy way in the practice and not actually be doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even in the suttas, the Buddha said, his disciples pay respect to him correctly by becoming arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: There were those statements in the suttas when a monk becomes an arahant and says the teacher has been respected, has been served, has been venerated, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you could spend the rest of your life bowing, but if you are not practicing, it makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just an external norm, an external compensation that you're trying to engage in, because you're not practicing.